Today on Polar Ice Creamy, we're going to dive
deeper into ice cream stabilizers and emulsifiers,
how you can create the Perfect Blend
so that you can make your homemade
ice cream sugar-free and low fat, plus it
lasts much longer in your freezer [Music]
So as we're talking science in this episode,
grab your coffee or your tea or whatever it else
is you want to drink and sit down because
we've got a lot to go through in here. I
think what we'll do first is, let's get some
stabilizers out onto the top here and we can
discuss them a bit further. So what we've got
here is a selection of ice cream stabilizers,
some of the more common ones, some I just
don't have here because I just don't use them,
but before we dive into these, let's look at
why you should use, and companies use ice cream
stabilizers. So large ice cream manufacturers
make their ice cream in bulk and get it in the
tubs and get it in their supermarkets it has
to stay in there for days weeks and even months
sometimes and you know what it's like you go
to a supermarket you grab your tub off the
shelf and you open it up at home you're really
excited, you got a movie on it's Friday night,
you you dig your spoon in and it's just loaded
with ice crystals, used to get that a lot with
Häagen Dazs and Ben & Jerry's because they used to
just use egg yolk to stabilize their ice cream and
that's fine for short-term custard based ice
creams because egg yolks aren't that good at
stabilizing ice cream for a long period of time.
That's why they're changing their approach to how
they stabilize their ice cream. Now most new ice
cream companies, new within the last 10 years,
will all use some kind of stabilizer, whether it
be egg yolks, starches, gums or a combination of
all of them. Some companies like to throw the net
out and just catch whatever comes in, they'll use
most of them. There's an ice cream shop locally
that has five stabilizers in their ice cream,
I mean it's it's a powdered ice cream mix and
this is what a lot of ice cream companies do,
they buy pre-made powdered or liquid bases add
in the flavor and churn it. That's not good but
you got companies like Van Leeuwen that change the
approach, Salt & Straw, Jeni's you know all those
companies make that ice cream in real time,
so they'll make their ice cream bases using
real ingredients in a real environment locally and
then distribute it out to their locations. Look at
their ingredients you will find the stabilizer in
there somewhere I promise you. Now these are all
predominantly natural there are a couple that are
borderline so let's just look at what we've got
here. We got tapioca starch (that will stand for
corn starch as well slightly different reactions
but both starches) Xantham gum, Guar gum,
Locust Bean Gum, Tara gum, Pectin, Glucomannan,
CMC and GMS, we've got two Carrageenans here
and turn it one around so you can see it,
and a catch all scenario so let's look at
these as a whole and then we'll break them
down individually because when you combine some
of these ingredients they do something special.
I've done a few videos on stabilizers so I'm
not going to go into too much detail about the
individual ones, if you want to see a video on
starches and gums, I'll put some links in the
description and I'll probably put some kind of
link up here that you can head back and look at
the ice cream stabilizer series there there's a
lot more detail on each individual item but here
we're looking at how to blend your own perfect
combination of stabilizers so that you can make
ice cream at home and it will last a good length
of time. Now when you start dropping sugars,
if you use even allulose, you're losing solids
important solids in your ice cream the solids is
what makes your ice cream creamy okay, if you were
to make sorbet, it has very few solids so it's not
creamy so you need something to create that body
and that effect of a creamy texture and you can
get that with sorbet, high fat ice cream doesn't
suffer with that problem because there's a lot of
fat, dairy fat and milk fat in that ice cream
so you get that creamy texture regardless but
what you then get is Ice Crystal formation. So
what you can do is you can buy an off the-shelf
combination such as this, this is a great one,
not affiliated with any of these suppliers here
but this is a great one. If you if you're not
really interested in combining buying different
ingredients and making something that's perfect,
if you just make ice cream at home and you want
it to be the best that it can be, buying off the
shelf ice cream stabilizer blend, you can buy it
from here Special Ingredients you can you can buy
it from Modernist Pantry, lots of companies out
there do predefined ice cream stabilizer blends,
then you don't have to worry. Are they perfect,
no they're not, will they get you where you
need to be, 90% of the time yes they will.
Some of these stabilizers will create gels on
their own and that's their way of increasing body
and ice cream. The stabilizers predominantly known
for creating gels on their own are Locust bean gum
which creates a weak forming gel, Iota and Kappa
carrageenan which form soft and stiff gels, so
Kappa carageenan creates a stiff slightly brittle
gel and Iota carrageenan creates a soft elastic
gel. Then you've got sodium alginate that creates
a rigid hard brittle gel itself, gelatin that
creates a brittle gel and finally pectin which is
this one that creates a brittle but sticky gel. OK
now all those create gels independently on their
own without combining any of the ingredients,
once you start combining ingredients you have
what's called a synergistic effect and that's
just a really ponsie way of saying things work
well together. A couple of examples of stabilizers
that create gels when combined with other gums
are Locust bean gum and Zanthan gum, Locust bean
gum and Kappa carrageenan, CMC and guar gum and
CMC and all carrageenans. Now do you want a gel
to form in your ice cream? the yes or no answer
isn't as straightforward as you might think.
If you're making a high fat Dairy based ice
cream then no you wouldn't want a gel to form
because there's no need for it and what you'll
end up having is an over viscous base that is
going to really struggle to churn, won't have a
lot of overrun and will actually likely go a bit
hard. If you're making a lowfat ice cream, yes
you would need a combination of stabilizers to
create some kind of gel and that's because there's
basically no fat in your ice cream you need to
form that gel, to create that body which gives the
impression of a creamy mouth feel and that is the
importance in a good sorbet versus a bad sorbet is
more like granita where it's really icy, big fat
chunky ice crystals not very nice in the mouth you
know it's just pretty uninspiring. But a really
good sorbet can taste almost as creamy as ice
cream because that free formed water is slightly
gelled to create body and when frozen, the sheer
strength of your machine, whether it be a home
machine or a commercial machine, creates small
ice crystals almost as small as ice cream and then
gives you that super smooth sorbet mouth feel. You
cannot get that without some form of stabilizer so
when you're making an ice cream from anything from
gelato all the way up to super high fat ice cream,
you still need to consider the Ice Crystal
formation. So when your ice cream is churning,
especially in your home machine, when you look
above..... I'll put a video up on the screen,
you can see the Dasher which is the actual paddle
inside that's turning and the outside walls
and the bottom of your freezing compartment, it
doesn't matter what your ice cream machine is it's
going to be the same, the outside wall and the
base will be much colder than the rest of your ice
cream base churning inside. So you've got this rim
of super cold ice cream around the edge so that
is much colder than the middle. As your Dasher is
turning, it's shearing that cold ice cream off the
wall and incorporating into the warmer ice cream
base inside. Now over the period of the churn,
the cold ice cream is warmed up again, that's
a thaw cycle, so that ice is thawing because
it's going into the warmer liquid and then it's
refreezing as it touches the wall. So already
what you're getting is the creation of small ice
crystals that are melting and then they're forming
larger ice crystals because they're freezing
much much slower and that process of churning,
slowly starts to cut through those ice crystals
and create smaller versions up until the point
where your ice cream is ready to draw from the
machine or take out. Drawing ice cream is the
commercial term for removing finished churned ice
cream from your machine. So on smaller machines
and lower quality machines, it takes much longer
to get to that minus -10°C -12°C draw temperature,
that's the ideal draw temperature for ice cream.
It takes much longer to get to that stage, so the
ice crystals have a much longer period of time to
get larger and larger and larger and that's why a
better quality machine will will produce better
quality ice cream because the ice crystals are
smaller. The ice crystal size is what makes you,
your friends and anyone else that's going to eat
your ice cream, feel much more luxurious because
the smaller the Ice Crystal, the smoother it is.
So with that in mind you should really consider
using something to stop that unless you're going
to churn your ice cream, put it in a tub
in the freezer and then eat it within a few
days. That's okay because stabilizers really
have more impact post that period so I make
so much ice cream that it sits in the freezer
for weeks on end but I know that every tub,
even if it's been there there for 2 months, I
can spoon some out and it's just as good as the
day it went in. So let's look at some classic
combinations of ice cream stabilizers [Music]
The most common commercial combination
of stabilizers is Locust bean gum,
Guar gum and Carrageenan (specifically Lambda
carageenan) and in that order you would use a
4:2:1 ratio. So four parts Locust bean gum, two
parts guar gum, one part Lambda carrageenan. What
do those individual stabilizers do when Blended
together? well Locust bean gum is incredibly
good at suppressing Ice Crystal formation, so
that means it's really really good at stopping
large ice crystals forming in the churning phase
and post churn as well whilst in your freezer.
Guar gum works with locust bean gum and actually
increases its effectiveness when combined. This is
that synergistic effect, they work together
to reduce Ice Crystal formation even more,
but guar gum actually has a better effect at
increasing viscosity, so that is thickening
free water in your ice cream base. That will make
your ice cream base slightly thicker once it's
chilled in the refrigerator and it will also make
it churn more effectively because it it's quicker
to cool down in your ice cream machine. And then
finally, the Lambda Carrageenan part of that mix
is more about the longevity of your ice cream.
So that slows the ice cream melt down somewhat
that means that if you have an ice cream you
haven't used stabilizers in and you scoop it
out of the tub and you put it in the bowl, by the
time you've sat down, you can see it's melting on
the bottom of the bowl already. Lambda carrageenan
actually slows that process down somewhat, holds
on to those fat and water molecules for a little
bit longer. Not every recipe will need the same
stabilizer, that's why we come back to the store
bought blends, if you're only making it at home,
you don't need to worry about all this, buy
a store bought blend and you're good to go.
Another great combination is one that uses the
same blend that we've just spoken about so Locust
bean gum, Gua gum and Lambda carrageenan, but you
can also add an emulsifier. So an emulsifier is
basically what's in egg yolks it's lecithin. You
can buy sunflower lecithin, Soy lecithin or egg
yolks. All of these things will do the same.
An emulsifier bonds the fat and water into a
stable emulsion and keeps it there for a period of
time. Like I said earlier in the video, egg yolk
isn't as good at doing this as sunflower lecithin,
that's much better soy lecithin is also probably
the best one as far as I'm concerned so if you're
going to add an emulsifier to your stabilizer
blend you would add four parts lecithin, four
parts Locust bean gum, two parts guar gum,
one part Lambda carrageenan. That kind of blend
is a great place to start and then you can
adjust to suit depending on what you're making.
Another great and simple combination is gelatin
and xantham gum, they both are reasonably good at
surpressing Ice Crystal formation but they have
different effects in how the ice cream lasts. So
gelatin is more important when the ice cream is
hard, so when it's in it's frozen state, that
stops free water movement in your tub so when
it's in the freezer opening and closing your
freezer to get other food out just creates a
freeze thaw cycle, so that increases the size the
ice crystals, so the gelatin will actually help
in that state and a Xanthan gum is a generalized
stabilizer which has a much stronger effect when
your ice cream starts to melt so as you
take it out the freezer, you scoop some,
you put it in a bowl as it starts to slowly melt
as you're eating it the xantham gum will slow that
action and make it melt slower. Guar gum does
the same thing but guar gum can have a taste,
I can't taste it personally but some guar gum
you buy in the stores can taste very.... beanie,
because that's where it comes from. There are lots
of combinations that you can use for ice cream
stabilizers, some work incredibly well on their
own like tara gum, it it's really good it has
this multi effect on Dairy based and plant-based
ice cream so tara gum is excellent as it stands,
the the pre-bought is really really good because
they're designed to try and capture to some degree
the best of both worlds so they're great for low
Dairy, High Dairy ,low fat, high fat, low sugar,
high sugar, they're designed to work with all
of those. Now some of you are going to be sat
there saying "yeah but Ben and jerry's don't do
it so why should I do it, I don't want to eat
artificial ingredients" like I said, all of these
are made from Plants, they're processed in a way
that a lot of things are processed, the Tara gum
is made from beans from the Tara tree, Guar gum,
you know locust bean gum, tapioca starch, people
that say you know ice cream stabilizers aren't
natural, this is an ice cream stabilizer.... it's
tapioca starch! Have you ever used corn starch in
a recipe? yeah likely you have you've thickened a
gravy or a sauce or something like that, it's the
same thing okay, don't overthink where they come
from because they're just natural products that
are adjusted in a factory (dried and powdered)
that's what I mean adjusted, excluding these two
which are GMS and CMC as I'm not a massive fan
of those. So I'm just going to move those off
the screen. All of these are pretty natural, you
can have negative effects with some of them, some
people can get an effect with them, some people
say that locust bean gum has an effect on them...
just don't use it. If you know that you can't have
carrageenan then don't use it, there are lots of
other options. Tara gum, just straight Locust
bean gum. If you can't have Locust bean gum, look
at your Xanthan gum and guar gums on their own,
without any other additions. They're excellent at
stabilizing ice cream, gaur gum creates a slightly
stretchy texture, I mean I'm really only talking
slightly here. It's ever so slightly stretchy
texture that's delicious in homemade ice cream the
higher fat or the the lower overrun that home ice
cream generally creates compared to commercial,
really benefits something like guar gum and
it's it's something if you've never used guar
gum try it. You can buy it on Amazon pretty much
all over the world. But to finish this video,
I'm going to remake this ice cream here "the
tonight dough Ben and& Jerry's" in avcoming video.
Let's just read the ingredients just so you
can feel at home with ice cream stabilizers,
the list is pretty long: Cream, concentrated
skimmed milk, sugars which include (cane sugar,
brown sugar, corn syrup) sweetened condensed
milk, black strap molasses, wheat flour, cocoa,
canola oil, frozen egg yolk, peanut butter,
water, liquid whole egg, butter, coconut oil,
soybean oil, unsweetened chocolate, salt, tapioca
flour, natural flavoring.... whatever that is,
baking soda, vanilla extract, cocoa butter,
soy lecithin, guar gum, carrageenan.
Gone of the days when the big boys refused to
stabilize their ice cream, you heard it in there,
that list of what's in there, that includes
the cookie dough as well as the ice cream,
but there's no way to break it down but I
guarantee you that they are using that opportunity
to stabilize their ice cream for longevity in the
stores. OK in there we know we had carrageenan,
we had guar gum ,we had lecithin which is an
emulsifier, it's the same stuff you're buying
in the stores so why not make it at home. OK, if
you have questions about combining stabilizers,
there's two excellent resources online. I'll
put links in the description where you can
have a read but as always, feel free to ask
me any questions you have about stabilizers
and combining them. There's enough knowledge
on my channel now for stabilizers themselves
so you can go back and look at those and decide on
which ones you want to use and combine. If you're
just starting out with combining stabilizers
in your ice cream, I recommend the standard
Locust bean gum, Guar gum and Carrageenan.
Finally the combination of egg yolks and
stabilizers, absolutely some people
say you don't need to with egg yolks,
you absolutely should consider it. Think of egg
yolks as an emulsifier rather than a stabilizer
because they're just not very good at stabilizing.
OK so with that in mind, I hope you enjoyed this
scientific look into the stabilization of ice
cream, gelato, sorbat, sherbet it's all the
same you'll just need a different stabilizer
and if you're not subscribed, then please make
sure you do, click that like button. Thanks very
much for watching and I will see you next week.
[Music]